<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ep-patent-document PUBLIC "-//EPO//EP PATENT DOCUMENT 1.1//EN" "ep-patent-document-v1-1.dtd">
<ep-patent-document id="EP78100151A1" file="EP78100151NWA1.xml" lang="en" country="EP" doc-number="0006091" kind="A1" date-publ="19800109" status="n" dtd-version="ep-patent-document-v1-1">
<SDOBI lang="en"><B000><eptags><B001EP>..BE..DE....FR....................................</B001EP><B005EP>B</B005EP></eptags></B000><B100><B110>0006091</B110><B120><B121>EUROPEAN PATENT APPLICATION</B121></B120><B130>A1</B130><B140><date>19800109</date></B140><B190>EP</B190></B100><B200><B210>78100151.6</B210><B220><date>19780614</date></B220><B230></B230><B240></B240><B250>en</B250><B251EP>en</B251EP><B260>en</B260></B200><B400><B405><date>19800109</date><bnum>198001</bnum></B405><B430><date>19800109</date><bnum>198001</bnum></B430></B400><B500><B510><B516>3</B516><B511> 3C 07C  97/10   A</B511><B512> 3C 07D 295/10   B</B512><B512> 3C 07C  49/84   B</B512><B512> 3C 08K   5/00   B</B512></B510><B540><B541>de</B541><B542>2-Hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl Benzophenone und deren Verwendung als Lichtschutzmittel in polymeren Zusammensetzungen; Verfahren zur Herstellung eines 5,5-Methylen bis (2-Hydroxy-4-alkoxy-benzophenon).</B542><B541>en</B541><B542>2-Hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenones and their use as photostabilisers in polymeric compositions, a process for preparing a 5,5-methylene bis (2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone).</B542><B541>fr</B541><B542>2-Hydroxy-4-alcoxy-5-aminométhyle benzophénones et leur application comme photo-stabilisants dans des compositions polymères; procédé de préparation d'un 5,5-méthylène bis (2-hydroxy-4-alcoxybenzophénone).</B542></B540><B560></B560></B500><B700><B710><B711><snm>S.A. Diamond Shamrock Benelux N.V.</snm><iid>00201860</iid><irf>KN 20</irf><syn>Diamond Shamrock Benelux N.V., S.A.</syn><adr><str>Chaussée de la Hulpe185</str><city>B-1170 Bruxelles</city><ctry>BE</ctry></adr></B711></B710><B720><B721><snm>Kubota, Naohiro</snm><adr><str>163 Seki</str><city>Urawa City
Saitama</city><ctry>JP</ctry></adr></B721><B721><snm>Shibata, Toshihiro</snm><adr><str>136-49-3-104 Naracho</str><city>Omiya City
Saitama</city><ctry>JP</ctry></adr></B721><B721><snm>Sugibuchi, Kazuo</snm><adr><str>3-25-10 Nakagawa</str><city>Adachi-ku
Tokyo</city><ctry>JP</ctry></adr></B721></B720><B740><B741><snm>Abitz, Walter, Dr.-Ing.</snm><sfx>et al</sfx><iid>00001202</iid><adr><str>Patentanwälte Abitz &amp; Partner
Postfach 86 01 09</str><city>81628 München</city><ctry>DE</ctry></adr></B741></B740></B700><B800><B840><ctry>BE</ctry><ctry>DE</ctry><ctry>FR</ctry></B840></B800></SDOBI><!-- EPO <DP n="1"> -->
<abstract id="abst" lang="en">
<p id="pa01" num="0001">2-Hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenones of formula:
<chemistry id="chema01" num="0001"><img id="ia01" file="imga0001.tif" wi="37" he="39" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>in which R is an alkyl group having 1 to 12 carbon atoms, and R, and R<sub>2</sub> taken together form a 5 to 6 member heterocyclic ring free of carbonyl substituents and including the nitrogen atom, or are independent hydrogen atoms or alkyl groups having 1 to 6 carbon atoms, provided that R, and R<sub>2</sub> are not simultaneously hydrogen, are described. They are prepared by reaction of a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-amino- methylbenzophenone with an amine and formaldehyde. The compounds can be used, alone or in combination with other stabilisers, to prevent photodegradation of organic materials, particularly as light stabilisers for synthetic resins.
<ul id="ula01" list-style="none">
<li>5,5-methylene bis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-benzophenone) of formula:
<chemistry id="chema02" num="0002"><img id="ia02" file="imga0002.tif" wi="37" he="51" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>wherein R ist an alkyl group having 1 to 12 carbon atoms is prepared by condensation of a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone with itself or with a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone. This compounds also are useful to prevent photodegradation of organic materials, particulary as stabilisers for synthetic resins.</li>
</ul></p>
</abstract><!-- EPO <DP n="2"> -->
<description id="desc" lang="en">
<p id="p0001" num="0001">This invention relates to 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone ultraviolet radiation absorbing compounds, to a process for preparing such compounds, to synthetic resins stabilized against the harmful effects of ultraviolet radiation by incorporating in such resins small quantities of such compounds, and to stabilizer compositions comprising such compounds in combination with a known polymer stabilizer.</p>
<p id="p0002" num="0002">Certain 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone compounds are known to be effective ultraviolet absorbers and light stabilizers, with the 2--hydroxyl group critically necessary for effectiveness. These are among a large number of classes of compounds disclosed in the patent ' literature as meeting the requirements for an effective ultraviolet radiation absorber. in lieu of individual references, the review by G. 2. Lappin in " Encyclopedia of Polymer Science and Technology " (N. Bikales, ed. New York, John Wiley-interscience, 1971) Vol. 14, pages 125 to 148 can be consulted.</p>
<p id="p0003" num="0003">According to Lappin's review, the 18 2-hydroxybenzophenone compounds indicated to be in commercial use as stabilizers are low to moderate molecular weight compounds having a single benzophenone unit in the molecule. Lappin refers to problems of "compatibility" of the additive stabilizer with the polymer being stabilized, including such properties as the solubility of the additive in the polymer, the rate of diffusion of the additive through the polymer, and the rate of loss of the additive from the polymer. Lappin characterizes compatibility as " a sensitive function of molecular structure and not entirely predictable". Among attempts to improve on the commercially available 2-hydroxybenzophenones. Lappin indicates that longer outdoor life of polymers might be obtained with relatively high molecular weight ultraviolet radiation absorbers <!-- EPO <DP n="3"> -->and states that attempts to utilize polymeric and polymerizable absorbers for this purpose had given ambiguous results and not been commercially successful.</p>
<p id="p0004" num="0004">Subsequent attempts to overcome the inadequacies of the conventional ultraviolet absorber stabilizers include a number of disclosures of 2-hydroxybenzophenones having either a plurality of benzophenone units in the molecule or functional group substitution in addition to hydroxyl and alkoxyl. Thus, Lappin in U.S. Patent 3,310,525 of March 21, 1967 disclosed alpha-omega-bis(2-hydroxybenzoyl)alkane stabilizers for polyesters and poly-alpha-olefin resins, having a formula
<chemistry id="chem0001" num="0001"><img id="ib0001" file="imgb0001.tif" wi="60" he="32" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>wherein n is an integer in a range from 2 to 8, and X, Y and Z are independently selected from the group of hydrogen, C<sub>t</sub>-C<sub>4</sub> alkoxy and C<sub>t</sub>-<sup>C</sup><sub>4</sub> alkyl radicals.
<ul id="ul0001" list-style="none">
<li>H. Dressler in U.S. Patent 3,399,237 of August 27, 1968 disclosed ultraviolet light stabilizing derivatives of 4-benzoylresorcinol having the formula
<chemistry id="chem0002" num="0002"><img id="ib0002" file="imgb0002.tif" wi="65" he="45" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>wherein Z is a member selected from the group consisting of sulfur and
<chemistry id="chem0003" num="0003"><img id="ib0003" file="imgb0003.tif" wi="15" he="11" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>and R is a member selected from the group consisting of hydrogen and alkyl having from 1-11 carbon atoms.</li>
<li>M. Minagawa in Japan Kokai 74 78,692 of July 29, 1974 disclosed 2-hydroxybenzophenone derivatives carrying cyclic imide substituents linked to the 4-position of the 2-hydroxybenzophenone by an alkyleneoxy group, for example 4-(2-phthalimidethoxy)-2-hydroxy- benzophenone.</li>
<li>M. Minagawa in Japan Kokai 75 74579 of June 19, 1975 disclosed 2-hydroxybenzophenone derivatives having from 2 to 7 hydroxybenzophenone units linked through such bivalent groups as methylene, methyleneoxymethylene, cyclohexylidene, sulfide, sulfinyl, sulfonyl, alkylidene, carboxyalkylidene, and carbalkoxyalkylidene, including for example methylenebis(2-hydroxy-<!-- EPO <DP n="4"> --></li>
<li>-4-methoxybenzophenone). The location of attachment of the bivalent linking group on the 2-hydroxybenzophenone unit is nowhere specified by Minagawa.</li>
<li>H. Hinagawa in Japan Kokai 75 86487 of July 11, 1975 disclosed 2-hydroxybenzophenone derivatives substituted in unspecified ring position with N-methylene cyclic amide and N-methylene cyclic imide groups.</li>
</ul></p>
<heading id="h0001">SUMMARY OF THE INVENTION</heading>
<p id="p0005" num="0005">In accordance with this invention a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone having 1 to 12 carbon atoms in the alkoxy group is caused to react with formaldehyde and an amine represented by the formula HNR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, In which R and R<sub>2</sub> taken together form a 5 to 6 member heterocyclic ring free of carbonyl groups and including the nitrogen atom, or are Independently hydrogen or alkyl groups having 1 to 6 carbon atoms, provided that R<sub>1 </sub>and R<sub>2</sub> are not simultaneously hydrogen.</p>
<p id="p0006" num="0006">This reaction provides a novel 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl- benzophenone represented by Formula I.
<chemistry id="chem0004" num="0004"><img id="ib0004" file="imgb0004.tif" wi="71" he="37" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry></p>
<p id="p0007" num="0007">In which <sub>R</sub>, R<sub>1</sub>, and R<sub>2 </sub>are as defined above.</p>
<p id="p0008" num="0008">The new 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone is an effective stabilizer for polymers such as polyamides, polyesters both saturated and unsaturated, polyacetals, polyolefins, and polyurethanes, as well as a catalyst for the conversion of organic isocyanates to isocyanurates (i.e. trimerized isocyanates). The 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl- <!-- EPO <DP n="5"> -->benzophenone can also react, suitably in the presence of an alkaline catalyst, with a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone or with itself to give a 5,5'-methylene bis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone) represented by formula II which can be recovered In high yield and purity while minimizing formation of less desirable isomers and by-products. Reactions for the preparation of a new 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-amino- methylbenzophenone (reaction A) and subsequent conversion to a 5,5'-methyienebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone) (reaction B) can be written as follows:
<chemistry id="chem0005" num="0005"><img id="ib0005" file="imgb0005.tif" wi="134" he="34" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>
<chemistry id="chem0006" num="0006"><img id="ib0006" file="imgb0006.tif" wi="135" he="94" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>X is hydrogen or -CH<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>. Thus, when X is hydrogen, reaction B is a condensation of 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone with 2-hydroxy-4 -alkoxybenzophenone to give 5,5'-tnethylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone; When X is -CH<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub>, the reaction can be written as a dimerization of self-condensation of 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone (reaction C) to give 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone) as follows:<!-- EPO <DP n="6"> -->
<chemistry id="chem0007" num="0007"><img id="ib0007" file="imgb0007.tif" wi="148" he="49" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>When the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone used in reaction A with amine and formaldehyde to make the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzo- phenone is different from the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone used in the condensation reaction B with the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl- benzophenone to give the methylene disubstituted benzophenone product, there can be obtained in an unambiguous and selective manner an unsymmetrical bis-benzophenone of the formula:
<chemistry id="chem0008" num="0008"><img id="ib0008" file="imgb0008.tif" wi="114" he="30" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry></p>
<p id="p0009" num="0009">in which R and R' are dissimilar alkyl groups having 1 to 12 carbon atoms, as illustrated by the following reaction sequence using first 2-hydroxy-4-n-oxtoxybenzophenone in the aminomethylation reaction, followed by the condensation of the aminomethyl derivative with 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone: .
<chemistry id="chem0009" num="0009"><img id="ib0009" file="imgb0009.tif" wi="152" he="78" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry></p><!-- EPO <DP n="7"> -->
<p id="p0010" num="0010">When a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone is used as a polymer stabilizer to protect a polymer against the harmful effects of light of wavelength less than 400 nanometers, effective concentrations In the polymer range from 0.01 to 1% by weight of the polymer being stabllized. Known polymer stabilizers can be used in combination with a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone of the invention in proportions of 0.1 part of known stabllizers up to 10 parts of known stabilizer per part of 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone.</p>
<heading id="h0002">DESCRIPTION OF THE PREFERRED EMBODIMENTS.</heading>
<p id="p0011" num="0011">In formula 1 of the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone of this invention, R, R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> can be for example methyl, ethyl, propyl, isopropyl, butyl, s-butyl, isobutyl, t-butyl, amyl, isoamyl, hexyl, 2-ethylbutyl, and 4-methylpent-2-yl. In addition R can be heptyl, n-octyl, isooctyl, 2-ethylhexyl, nonyl , decyl, n-dodecyl , etc..</p>
<p id="p0012" num="0012">As examples of amines HNR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub> used in this invention, one can cite monomethylamine, monoethylamine, monopropylamine, monobutylamine, dimethylamine, diethylamine, di-n-propylamine, diisopropylamine, di-n-butylamine, di-t-butylamine, diisobutylamine, diamylamine, ethylmethylamine, ethylisopropylamine, morpholine, pyrrolidine and piperidine, the last three representing amines in which R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> taken together from a 5 to 6 member ring free of carbonyl groups.</p>
<p id="p0013" num="0013">All forms of formaldehyde can be used in the process of this invention, such as gaseous formaldehyde, aqueous solution of formaldehyde, paraformaldehyde, trioxane, tetraoxymethylene and other solid forms of formaldehyde.</p>
<p id="p0014" num="0014">The entry of the aminomethyl group in the 5 position of the 2-hydroxy--4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to this invention is unusual and unexpected, since theusual aminomethylation of phenols occurs ortho to the phenolic hydroxyl as long as an open ortho position is available.</p><!-- EPO <DP n="8"> -->
<p id="p0015" num="0015">Each stage of. the process of the invention is preferably carried out in the presence of an organic solvent. Solvents that can be used in . this invention preferably boil between 60° and 210°C, and include alcohols such as methanol, ethanol, isopropanol, n-butanol, 2-ethylhexanol, 2-methoxyethanol , 2-ethoxyethanol, 2-butoxyethanol , and 1-methoxy-2-propanol; aliphatic hydrocarbons such as hexane and heptane; aromatic hydrocarbons such as benzene, toluene, and xylene; hydrocarbon mixtures such as mineral spirits; and cyclic ethers such as furan, tetrahydrofuran, dioxane, and trioxane. Commercial grade solvents which can contain moisture are satisfactory for use without pretreatment. The proportion of solvent can suitably range from 5% to 5000% by weight of the combined reacting materials.</p>
<p id="p0016" num="0016">As examples of alkaline catalyst used in the process of this invention, one may cite alcoholates such as sodium methylate and sodium ethylate, also sodium hydroxide, potassium hydroxide, potassium carbonate and sodium carbonate ; any compound whose 1% aqueous solution has apH of 10 or higher is satisfactory as an alkaline catalyst.</p>
<p id="p0017" num="0017">Each reaction stage of the process of this Invention is carried out at a temperature within the range of -10°C to 200°C, preferably 20°C t0 120°C.</p>
<p id="p0018" num="0018">The proportions of reacting materials in the process of the invention are as shown in reactions A, B, and C above. Any of the reagents can be used in excess to maximize the extent of conversion of the other ingredients, particularly the relatively costly 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone.</p>
<p id="p0019" num="0019">The order of addition of reacting matarials to the mixture is not critical and can be adjusted for the sake of convenience.</p>
<p id="p0020" num="0020">New 2-hydroxy-4-alcoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenones represented by Formula that can be prepared in accordance with this invention include:
<ul id="ul0002" list-style="none">
<li>2-hydroxy-4-ethoxy-5-dimethylaminomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-isopropoxy-5-piperidinomethylbenzophenone<!-- EPO <DP n="9"> --></li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-n-butoxy-5-diethylaminomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-5-morpholinomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-n-decyloxy-5-N,N-dibutylaminomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-n-heptoxy-5-pyrrolidinomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-n-dodecyloxy-5-diisopropylaminomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-isodacyloxy-5-dimethylaminomethylbanzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-5-S-butylaminomethylbenzophenone</li>
<li>2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-5-N,N-di-n-hexylaninomethylibenzophenone.</li>
<li>5,5'-Methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenones) represented by formula</li>
<li>II that can be prepared in accordance with-this invention include</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-ethoxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-propoxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-isobutoxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-amyloxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5.5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-(2-ethylhexyloxy)benzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-nonyloxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-isodecyloxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-dodecyloxybenzophenone)</li>
<li>as well as the following new unsymmetrical bis-benzophenones</li>
<li>represented by formula III
<chemistry id="chem0010" num="0010"><img id="ib0010" file="imgb0010.tif" wi="144" he="87" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry> <!-- EPO <DP n="10"> --> 
<chemistry id="chem0011" num="0011"><img id="ib0011" file="imgb0011.tif" wi="143" he="44" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry></li>
</ul></p>
<p id="p0021" num="0021">The following Examples describe the preparation of particularly preferred 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-amino-methylbenzophenones represented by Formula I and 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenones) represented by Formula II.</p>
<heading id="h0003">EXAMPLE - I</heading>
<p id="p0022" num="0022">Preparation of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone 228.3 g (1.0 mole) of 2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-benzophenone, 146.3 (1.3 moles, 40% aqueous solution) of dimethylamine, 105.4 g (1.3 moles, 37% aqueous solution ) of formalin and 1200 ml of methanol was put Into a flask, dissolved and heated under stirring at reflux temperature (68 to 70°C) for 6 hours. When solvent was vacuum distilled off, 285gr of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone was obtained. The product had m.p. 69°C, infrared-absorption at 1620 (Carbonyl), 2760 and 2800 (N-CH group) wave numbers, and neutralization equivalent (as nitrogen) 4.89% (Calculated 4.91%). The NMR spectrum provided evidence for the 5-position of the dimethylaminomethyl group.</p>
<heading id="h0004">EXAMPLE - 2</heading>
<heading id="h0005">Preparation of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-n-octoxybenzophenone</heading>
<p id="p0023" num="0023">16.3g of 2-hydroxy-4-octoxybenzophenone, 7.3gr (40% aqueous solution) of dimethyl amine, 5.3gr (37% aqueous solution) of formalin and 100ml of butanol as solvent was put Into a flask, dissolved and heated at 70°C for 8 hours. After cooling, an excess of dimethyl amine, formalin, <!-- EPO <DP n="11"> -->butanol and water was vacuum distilled to give a residue of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-n-octoxybenzophenone having m.p. 55-62°C, infra-red absorption at 1620(carbonyl), 2760 and 2810 (N-CH group) wave numbers, and neutralization equivalent 3.63% N (calculated 3.65%).</p>
<heading id="h0006">EXAMPLE - 3</heading>
<heading id="h0007">Preparation of 5-diethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone</heading>
<p id="p0024" num="0024">22.8g of 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone, 9.5g of diethylamine, 10.5g of formalin 37% solution and 30 cc of isopropanol were heated at 81.5°C reflux for 2.5 hours then solvent was distilled off and 30.1g of 5-diethyl aminomethyl -2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone was obtained. The product had m.p. 78-79<sup>0</sup>C, infra-red absorption(C=0) 1630, (N-CH) 2810 wave numbers, and nitrogen 4.44% (Calc. 4.47).</p>
<heading id="h0008">EXAMPLE - 4</heading>
<heading id="h0009">Preparation of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone) by catalytic dimerization</heading>
<p id="p0025" num="0025">28.6g of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone, 40ml of Pegasol 3040 (aliphatic hydrocarbon, b.<sup>p.</sup> 155 to 204°C, Mobil Chemical Co.) and 10ml of 2-ethylhexanol was put into a flask, dissolved, added 0.5gr of sodium methoxide and heated at 120 to 125°C under stirring for 15 hours. After cooling, 50ml of acetone was added and filtered. The obtained crystal was dispersed in 80ml of water containing 0.5% acetic acid and treated at 80°C for 3 hours.</p>
<p id="p0026" num="0026">17.5g (yield: 74.8%) of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone yellow crystalline fine as a powder with melting point of 229 to 230°C was obtained after filtration and drying. The NMR spectrum provided evidence that the methylene group was attached to the 5 and 5' positions of the two 2-hydroxy-benzophenone groups.<!-- EPO <DP n="12"> --></p>
<heading id="h0010">EXAMPLE - 5-</heading>
<heading id="h0011">Preparation of 5,5'-methylenebis (2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone) from 5-dimethylominomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone and 2-hydroxy--4-methoxybenzophenone.</heading>
<p id="p0027" num="0027">14.25 gr (0.05 mole) of 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone, 11.4 gr (0.05 mole) of 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone and 35 ml of n-butanol was put into a flask, dissolved, added 1ml of sodium methoxide (28% methanol solution) and heated at reflux temperature (95 to 105°C) under nitrogen atmosphere for 12 hours. After cooling, 30 ml of acetone was added. The precipitated product was filtered. 19.4g (yield: 83.1%) of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone as a yellow fine powder with melting point of 228 to 230°C was obtained, identical with the product of Example 4 by mixed melting point and infra-red absorption spectrum.</p>
<heading id="h0012">EXAMPLE - 6 -</heading>
<heading id="h0013">Preparation of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-octyloxybenzophenone).</heading>
<p id="p0028" num="0028">The crude 5-dimethylaminomethyl-2-hydroxy-4-n-octyloxybenzophenone obtained as described in Example 2 from 16.3<sub>9</sub> of 2-hydroxy-4-n-octyl--oxybenzophenone was combined with 16.3gr of 2-hydroxy-4-octoxybenzophenone, 1gr of NaOH and 100ml of xylene, then heated at 130°C under nitrogen atmosphere for 13 hours, and then cooled, vacuum distilled to remove xylene. Toluene 200ml was added and the mixture washed with water several times, and then dried and stripped to remove toluene.</p>
<p id="p0029" num="0029">A high viscous reaction product was obtained. Hexane was added and heated until completely dissolved, and then cooled and filtered. 23.0<sub>9</sub> (yield: 72.5%) of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-n-octyloxybenzophenone as yellow needle crystals with melting point of 102 to 103 C was obtained.<!-- EPO <DP n="13"> --></p>
<heading id="h0014">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE - 1-</heading>
<p id="p0030" num="0030">22.8gr (0.1 mole) of 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone, 6.lgr (0.075 mole, 37% aqueous solution) of formal in and 0.6g of conc. H<sub>2</sub>S0<sub>4</sub> as cataTyst was put Into a flask and heated under stirring at reflux temperature for 13 hours. A high viscous reaction product was obtained. After cooling to room temperature, 20ml of methanol was added, heated to remove impurities and washed with water. A yellow fine powder was obtained. The fine powder was recrystallized from toluene solution for three times, obtaining 4.7g(yield:19.9%) of yellow fine powder with melting point of 202 to 209°C.</p>
<heading id="h0015">COMPARATIVE EXAMPLE - 2</heading>
<p id="p0031" num="0031">22.8gr (0.1 mole) of 2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone and 200ml of dichloromethane as solvent was put into a flask, dissotved and then HCl gas was bubbled into the mixture under stirring at room temperature for 6 hours. After completion of the bubbling, the mixture was heated under stirring at 30 to 35°C for 4 hours. The mixture was washed with water, solvent off and 20ml of ethanol was added, heated to remove impurities. A yellow powder was obtained by retreatment with ethanol. The powder was recrystallized from toluene solution for two times, obtaining 3.1g (yield: 13.2%) of yellow fine powder with mlting point of 196 to 201°C.</p>
<p id="p0032" num="0032">It is readily seen that the use as intermediates of the 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenones of this invention enables the preparation of 5,5'-methylenebis(2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenones) to be carried out with greatly improved yield and purity of product.</p>
<p id="p0033" num="0033">Synthetic resins that can be stabilized with compositions comprising a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone and a known polymer stabilizer according to this invention include alphaolefin polymers such as polyethylene, polypropylene, polybutene, poly-3-methylbutene,or copolym <!-- EPO <DP n="14"> -->thereof such as ethylene-vinylacetate copolymer, ethy- lenepropylene copolymer, polystyrene, polyvinylacetate, acrylic ester resins, copolymers from styrene and another monomer ( for example, maleic anhydride, butadiene, acrylonitrile and so on), acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene copolymer, acrylic acid ester- butadiene-styrene copolymer, methacrylic acid ester-butadiene-styrene copolymer, methacrylate ester resin such as polymethylmethacrylate, polyvinylalcohol, ethylene and butylene terephthalate polyesters, polyamide, polycarbonate, polyacetal, polyurethane, cellulosic resin, or phenolic resin, urea resin, melamlne resin, epoxy resin, unsaturated polyester, silicone resin, halogen- containing resins such as polyvinyl chloride, polyvinylidene chloride, polyvinylidene fluoride and copolymers thereof, and further rubbers such as isoprene rubber chloroprene rubber, and blends of the above resins.</p>
<p id="p0034" num="0034">Stabilizer compositions comprising a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl- benzophenone and a known polymer stabilizer according to this invention can be formulated and marketed In liquid, solid, and paste forms. An inert solvent can be used to facilitate handling. The 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone and known polymer stabilizer can also be solubilized in one another by heating, such as at 70-160<sup>0</sup>C up to 4 hours, and then allowing the resulting melt to cool and harden sufficiently to be flaked and ground.</p>
<p id="p0035" num="0035">Known polymer stabilizers can be used In synthetic resin compositions together with the stabilizer compositions of this invention and can be admixed with the latter. Such known stabilizers include phenols, thiodipropior acid esters, polyvalent metal salts of carboxylic acids, organic phos- phitcs, and 1,2-epoxides.</p>
<p id="p0036" num="0036">As examples of the phenols suited for use in this invention, one may cite the following: 2,6-di-tertiarybutyl-p-cresol, stearyl-(3,5-di-methyl-4-hydroxybenzyl)thioglycolate. <!-- EPO <DP n="15"> -->stearyl-beta(4-hydroxy-3,5-di-tertiary butylphenyl) propionate, distearyl-(4-hydroxy-3-methyl-5-tertiary butyl) benzylmalonate, 2,2'-methylenebis(4-methyl-t-tertiary butylphenol), 4,4'-methylenebis(2,6-di-tertiary butylphenol), 2,2'-methylene bis(6-(1-methyicyclohexyl)-p-cresol), bis (3,3-bis(4-hydroxy-3-tertiary butylphenyl) butyric acid) glycol ester, 4,4'-butylidenebis(6-tertiary butyl-m-cresol), 1,1,3-tris(2-methyl-4-hydroxy-5-tertiary butylphenyl)butane, 1,3,5-tris(3,5-di-tertiary butyl-4-hydroxybenzyl)-2,4,6--trimethylbenzene, tetrakis(methylene-3-(3,5-di-tertiary butyl--4-hydroxyphenyl) propionate)methane, 1,3,5-tris(3,5-di-tertiary butyl-4-hydroxybenzyl)isocyanurate, 1,3,5-tris (3,5-di-tertiary butyl) 4- hydroxyphenyl) propionyloxyethyl) isocyanurate, 2-octylthio-4,6-di(4-hydroxy-3,5-di-tertiary butyl) phenoxy-1,3,5-triazine, and 4,4'-thiobis(6-tertiary butyl-m-cresol).</p>
<p id="p0037" num="0037">A comprehensive disclosure of useful phenols by H. Hinagawa et al In U.S. Patent 3,907,517 column 17 line 64 to column 23 line 61 is here incorporated by reference. When phenols are used, the concentration per 100 parts of polyolefin resin can range from 0.01 to about 0.5 part by weight.</p>
<p id="p0038" num="0038">Representative thiodipropionic acid esters include di-n dodecyl thiodipropionate, dihexadecyl thiodipropionate, distearyl thiodipropionate, n-octyl eicosanyl thiodipropionate and n-octadecyl cyclohexane-1,4-dimethanol thiodipropionate polyester. A comprehensive disclosure of useful thiodipropionate esters by M. Hinagawa et al In U.S. Patent 3,869,423, column 17 line 55 to column 19 line 54 is here incorporated by reference.</p><!-- EPO <DP n="16"> -->
<p id="p0039" num="0039">Representative polyvalent metal salts include zinc, calcium, magnesium, barium, strontium and nickel salts of monocarboxylic acids having 6 to 24 carbon atoms, for example zinc benzoate, calcium palmitate, and nickel 2-ethylbutyrate. A comprehensive disclosure of useful metal salts by M. Minagawa et al in U.S. Patent 3,869,423, column 19 line 56 to column 20 line 35 is here incorporated by reference.</p>
<p id="p0040" num="0040">Representative organic phosphites include triisodecylphosphite, tris (nonylphenyl phosphite), and 4,4'-isopropylidene di<sup>p</sup>henol C12-C15 mixed alkyl phosphite. A comprehensive disclosure of useful organic phosphites by M. Minagawa et al in U.S. Patent 3,849,370 column 13 line 63 to column 16 line 48 is here incorporated by reference.</p>
<p id="p0041" num="0041">Representative 1,2-epoxides include epoxysoybean oil, epoxylinseed oil, and 2-ethylhexyl epoxystearate. A comprehensive disclosure of 1,2- epoxides by M. Minagawa et al in U. S. Patent 3,869,423 column 26 line 13 to line 39 is here incorporated by reference.</p>
<p id="p0042" num="0042">The preparation of the stabilized resin composition is easily accomplished by conventional procedures. A heated two roll mill, for example, is a convenient compounding tool for blending stabilizer compositions of the invention with polyolefins, vinyl chloride polymers, ABS polymers, ethylene-vinyl acetate copolymers and others.</p>
<p id="p0043" num="0043">The following Examples illustrate the use of polymer stabilizer compositions of the invention.</p>
<heading id="h0016">EXAMPLE - 7</heading>
<p id="p0044" num="0044">A premix of polybutylene terephthalate, 100 parts, tris-nonylphenyl- phosphite 0.1 part, and 2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-5-dimethylaminomethylbenzo- phenone 0.25 part was processed by injection molding at 270°C to prepare dumbbell specimens. Using these specimens, retention of tensile <!-- EPO <DP n="17"> -->strength after 500 hours in radiation was measured.</p>
<p id="p0045" num="0045">The retention of tensile strength of this composition was greater than that of a control composition omitting the 2-hydroxy-4-methoxy-5-dimethylamlnomethylbenzophenone.</p>
<heading id="h0017">EXAMPLE - 8</heading>
<p id="p0046" num="0046">A compound of ASS resin, 100 parts, zinc stearate 0.5 part, 4,4'--thiobis(2-t-butyl-5-methylphanol) 0.2 part and 5-diethylaminomethyl--2-hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone was milled and molded to obtain a sheet 3mm thick. On portions of this sheet the tensile strength before and after Irradiation for 800 hours in the weatherometer was measured.</p>
<p id="p0047" num="0047">The above composition had superior retention of tensile strength compared to a control composition lacking the 5-diethylaminomethyl-2--hydroxy-4-methoxybenzophenone of this invention.</p>
<heading id="h0018">EXAMPLE- 9</heading>
<p id="p0048" num="0048">A compound of high density polyethylene 100 parts by weight, calcium stearate 0.3 parts, distearyl thiodipropionate 0.2 part and 2-hydroxy-4-n-octoxy-5-dimethylaminomethylbenzophenone 0.1 part was milled and compression molded to give a sheet 0.5 mm thick. Portions of the sheet were exposed to the radiation of a weatherometer until embrittled.</p>
<p id="p0049" num="0049">The above composition outlasted a control composition made without the 2-hydroxy-4-octoxy-5-dimethylaminomethylbenzophenone.</p>
</description><!-- EPO <DP n="18"> -->
<claims id="claims01" lang="en">
<claim id="c-en-0001" num="">
<claim-text>1) A 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzephenone represented by the formula:
<chemistry id="chem0012" num="0012"><img id="ib0012" file="imgb0012.tif" wi="36" he="38" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>in which R is an alkyl group having 1 to 12 carbon atoms, and R and R<sub>2</sub> taken together form a 5 to 6 member heterocyclic ring free of carbonyl substituents and including the nitrogen atom, or are independently hydrogen atoms or alkyl groups having 1 to 6 carbon atoms, provided that R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are not simultaneously hydrogen.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0002" num="">
<claim-text>2) A 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to Claim 1 in which R is methyl.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0003" num="">
<claim-text>3) A 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to Claim 1 in which R is n-octyl.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0004" num="">
<claim-text>4) A 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to Claim 1 in which R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are methyl.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0005" num="">
<claim-text>5) A 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to Claim 1 in which R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> are ethyl.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0006" num="">
<claim-text>6) A process for preparing 5,5'-methylene bis (2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone) represented by the formula:
<chemistry id="chem0013" num="0013"><img id="ib0013" file="imgb0013.tif" wi="40" he="47" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry> <!-- EPO <DP n="19"> --> in which R is an alkyl group having 1 to 12 carbon atoms comprising the steps of treating a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone . of Claim I with a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone represented by the formula
<chemistry id="chem0014" num="0014"><img id="ib0014" file="imgb0014.tif" wi="42" he="27" img-content="chem" img-format="tif" inline="no"/></chemistry>in which R is an alkyl group having 1 to 12 carbon atoms and X is hydrogen or -CH<sub>2</sub>NR<sub>1</sub>R<sub>2</sub> in the presence of an organic solvent, removing the solvent, and recovering the 5,5'-methylenebis (2-hydroxy-4-alkoxybenzophenone).</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0007" num="">
<claim-text>7) A process according to Claim 6 in which X is hydrogen.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0008" num="">
<claim-text>8) A process according to Claim 6 in which X is -CH<sub>2</sub>N(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>-</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0009" num="">
<claim-text>9) A process according to Claim 6 in which the solvent is a hydrocarbon having a boiling point of 60 to 210°C.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0010" num="">
<claim-text>10)A process according to Claim 6 in which the solvent is an alcohol having a boiling point between 60 and 210°C.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0011" num="">
<claim-text>11) A process according to Claim 6 in which the reactants are brought together in the presence of an alkaline catalyst.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0012" num="">
<claim-text>12) A stabilized synthetic resin composition having increased resistance to deterioration on exposure to light of wavelength less than 400 nanometers, comprising a synthetic resin and 0.01 to 1% of a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone according to Claim 1.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0013" num="">
<claim-text>13) A stabilized synthetic resin composition according to Claim 12 in which the synthetic resin is an olefin polymer, a polyester, or a copolymer of acrylonitrile with butadiene and styrene.<!-- EPO <DP n="20"> --></claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0014" num="">
<claim-text>14) A stabilizer composition capable of enhancing the resistance to deterioration cn exposure of a synthetic resin to light of wavelength less than 400 nanometers comprising a 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethyl- benzophenone according to Claim 1 and from 0.1 to 10 parts by weight per part of 2-hydroxy-4-alkoxy-5-aminomethylbenzophenone of a known polymer stabilizer selected from the group consisting of phenols, thiodipropionic acid ester, polyvalent metal salts of carboxylic acids, organic phosphites, and 1 ,2-epoxides.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0015" num="">
<claim-text>15) A stabilizer composition according to Claim 14 in which the polymer stabilizer is a phenol.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0016" num="">
<claim-text>16) A stabilizer composition according to Claim 14 in which the polymer stabilizer is a thiodipropionic acid ester.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0017" num="">
<claim-text>17) A stabilizer composition according to Claim 14 in which the polymer stabilizer is a polyvalent metal salt of a monocarboxylic acid having 6 to 24 carbon atoms.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0018" num="">
<claim-text>18) A stabilizer composition according to Claim 14 in which the polymer stabilizer is an organic phosphite.</claim-text></claim>
<claim id="c-en-0019" num="">
<claim-text>19) A stabilizer composition according to Claim 14 in which the polymer stabilizer is a 1,2-epoxide.</claim-text></claim>
</claims><!-- EPO <DP n="21"> -->
<search-report-data id="srep" lang="en" srep-office="EP" date-produced=""><doc-page id="srep0001" file="srep0001.tif" wi="173" he="270" type="tif"/><!-- EPO <DP n="22"> --><doc-page id="srep0002" file="srep0002.tif" wi="178" he="266" type="tif"/></search-report-data>
</ep-patent-document>